Understanding the context window is like
the most key information you can
possibly take on if you're a dev working
with AI. And yet, a lot of devs are not
really clear on what a context window
is. If that is you, you are in the right
place. The context window is made up of
input and output tokens. The input
tokens might include a system prompt
here and let's say a user prompt, the
message from the user, and then the
output tokens is whatever the assistant
comes back with. This might involve
reasoning tokens as well or just pure
output tokens. The context window is not
any part of this. It's the whole thing.
The input and output tokens make up the
context window. Now, as the conversation
gets longer, as more and more messages
get put into the conversation, the
number of tokens used grows. And as you
can imagine, this can't go on forever.
Every model has a hard-coded limit for
the number of tokens it can see at any
one time. And if we imagine a super long
conversation here, eventually we will
hit a limit. And if you try to query the
LLM with this super long conversation
and you hit the limit, then you will
probably get some kind of error back
from the API. You might even hit the
limit during the generation of a
message. So this message might start
outside the context window limit, but as
it goes, oh, it carries on carries on
until it hits the context window limit.
The model itself isn't quite smart
enough to work around its own context
window limits. And so you will hit
issues like this sometimes. But the
biggest issue with context windows is
that the bigger they get, the more
lostinthe-middle issues you get. If we
imagine a huge conversation here where
these rings are the individual messages,
the messages at the start of the history
have quite a big impact on the output
and the ones at the end do too, but the
stuff in the middle the LLM pays a bit
less attention to. This is a well-known
phenomenon and it's much more pronounced
the larger the context window gets. So
when you're assessing a model, you
shouldn't just think, "Wow, this context
window limit's huge. That's incredible.
I can put so much stuff in there." that
model will still probably have lost in
the middle issues. It may even have
trouble retrieving information from its
own context window. And so even if that
model supports a big context window,
you'll definitely still get better
results from using fewer tokens in the
context. So that's what the context
window is and what its limitations are.
Thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next